Stewart Alsop Papers
Stewart Alsop Papers
1945-1967
Alsop, Stewart
1.25 linear ft.
Correspondence, notes, manuscripts, speeches and published and unpublished material of Stewart Alsop. Includes interviews with John F. Kennedy, Lyndon B. Johnson and others.
2738240
Biographical History
Stewart Johonnot Oliver Alsop (1914-1974) was an American newspaper columnist and political analyst. A graduate of Yale University (1936), he was an editor at Doubleday. After the United States entered World War II, Alsop joined the British Army, because his high blood pressure precluded his joining the United States Army. Later, Alsop was allowed to transfer to the U.S. Army and went to work for the Office of Strategic Services. For his work with the French Resistance, he was awarded the Croix de Guerre with Palm.
From 1945 to 1958, Stewart Alsop was co-writer, with his elder brother Joseph Alsop, of the "Matter of Fact" column for the New York Herald Tribune. Alsop went on to write articles and a regular column for the Saturday Evening Post until 1968, then a weekly column for Newsweek from 1968 to 1974. During this time period, he also wrote a regular column for the New York Times.
In addition to his work as a journalist, he is also the author of several books on politics and journalism.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Stewart Alsop Papers consists of correspondence, printed material, writings and miscellanea. Included in the collection is material related to Alsop's interviews with John F. Kennedy, Lyndon B. Johnson, Dean Rusk and others.
Correspondence consists of correspondence from and to Stewart Alsop.
Printed material contains a clipping of one of Alsop's articles.
Writings consists of notes and drafts, speeches and unpublished manuscripts. Notes and drafts contains Alsop's notes and drafts for a number of his articles, as well as transcripts of interviews he conducted with John F. Kennedy, Lyndon B. Johnson and various others. Also contained are Alsop's notes and briefing information for his trip to Vietnam during the earlier stages of American involvement there.
Miscellaneous contains a press statement from Gordon Dean, a copy of Alsop's passport application and a copy of a Paris directory (undated).
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged alphabetically by format (correspondence, printed material, writings, miscellaneous); correspondence is further arranged chronologically while writings is further arranged alphabetically.
Related Material
has the papers of a number of journalists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Journalism; Military history; Alsop, Stewart.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963; Cuban Missile Crisis, 1962--In mass media -- History -- 20th century.; Journalists -- United States.; Nuclear weapons -- Political aspects.; Nuclear weapons -- Press coverage -- United States -- History.; Press and politics -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Interviews.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Press coverage -- United States.; United States -- History -- 1945-1953.; United States -- History -- 1953-1961.; United States -- History -- 1961-1969.; Articles.; Correspondence.; Interviews.; Manuscripts for publication.; Research notes.; Speeches (documents); Journalists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Stewart Alsop, 1966, 1968.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - [General], 1945-1958; 9 folders (Box 1)
  - [General], Undated (Box 1)
- Printed materials
  - Revolution on Main Street (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Notes and drafts
    - The collapse of Kennedy's grand design, 6 Apr 1963 (Box 1)
    - Cuba - In time of crisis, 8 Dec 1962 (Box 1)
    - The great transition, 15 Feb 1964 (Box 2)
    - President Kennedy's grand strategy, 31 Mar 1962 (Box 2)
    - The president's next big decision, 25 Mar 1967; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - The trouble with the State Department, 3 Mar 1962 (Box 2)
    - The White House insiders, 10 Jun 1961 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Speeches
    - 1953 (Box 2)
    - 1956, 1960, 1963, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Undated (Box 3)
  - Unpublished manuscript
    - [Untitled], on hydrogen bomb development (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)